Hi. Guess what? If I lived in Victoria,
which I don't, but if I did, Victoria,
Australia that is, which is another
state here, I live in New South Wales,
far superior state, by the way.
Anyway, if I lived in Victoria,
it would be a now illegal as of
yesterday for me to call myself a
professional
engineer. I know that I'm a now
professional YouTuber, but anyway, it'd
be illegal for me to call myself a
professional engineer. And hi to all my
Victorian viewers, congratulations. You
better remove that title from your
resume or from any of your LinkedIn or
anywhere else unless you're registered,
I guess. So, thanks for someone on
Twitter for pointing this out. The
Professional Engineers Registration Bill
2019 in the Parliament of Victoria looks
like it just passed
yesterday. So, congratulations. Um there
was I had heard nothing about this.
There was a discussion period or
something like that, which um has ended
and it is now passed and everything in
here now applies to any Well, not any
engineer. Let's go down and take a look.
Applies to structural engineering, civil
engineering, mechanical engineering,
electrical engineering, fire safety
engineering, and any other prescribed
area of engineering. What is I'm not
quite sure what that means. Does that
mean like computer engineers, software
engineers? What Like are they just Is
this an all-encompassing term for
anything? I don't know. So, just a
little bit of background here. I've
actually done a video 1175 for those
playing along at home, how to become a
professional engineer. I'll link it in
at the end and down below. If you
haven't seen it, highly recommend. Goes
through all the different types of
specifically to electronics uh
engineering, the different levels of
engineering, the different uh
qualifications and things like that of
electronics engineers. Now, I'm not
talking about other aspects of
engineering here I might mention in a
minute, but electronics
electrical engineers working on, you
know, circuit design. Whether or not you
call yourself an electronics engineer or
an electrical engineer doesn't really
matter. Technically, I'm an electrical
engineer by qualification, but
you know, whatever. I've always been an
electronics engineer. But, that's just,
you know, academic. A lot of electronics
engineering courses are called
electrical engineering. It's just the
generic term for it which this new bill
encompasses. So, as I explained in this
video, we actually have a long rich
history here in Australia for electrical
electronics engineers in the
business. Many of them are unqualified.
Countless engineers, you do not need
engineering qualifications to become a
professional
electronics
electrical design engineer here
in Australia. I know that's very
different in other countries. It is very
regimented. They have very similar laws
and bills like that has just passed in
Victoria here. But, we've been operating
up until now that anyone in Australia
can call themselves an engineer. I
realize where this
bill comes from cuz we've had a recent
huge like it's made national news in
Australia in the last year or two about
how we've had all sorts of building
faults, both commercial and in
particular residential buildings like
apartments, units, things like that.
They're not building them up to scratch
and they're falling down, they're
crumbling. Some say a national crisis
here in Australia of about these shoddy
buildings that have gone up. So, I know
where this has come from and I fully
support this kind of stuff for things
that have to do with our safety like
buildings, bridges, all that sort of
jazz. Now, unfortunately or fortunately,
depends on what your opinion is, leave
your opinion down below. Um, this now
encompasses electrical engineering and
almost by definition, my job,
electronics design engineering. And most
of my audience, that's what we do. We do
electrical  electronics
engineering design. And this is kind of
being caught up in that, as has like
basic mechanical engineering now. So, I
yeah,
this has been caught up in this
structural and civil engineering thing
that's
everyone in Australia is going crazy
about. And unfortunately, it's passed in
Victoria, and it sounds like it may be
the catalyst for it to happen
Australia-wide. So, I'm not personally
affected yet, but everyone, all my
viewers in Victoria, certainly will be
as of yesterday. But let's just have a
look at what the offenses are, shall we?
Part five. Offense to provide
professional engineering services
without registration. One, a person must
not provide professional engineering
services in a particular area of
engineering. I assume that means the
list above, including electrical and
almost by definition, electronics,
really. In an area or providing the
professional engineering services under
the direct supervision of a person who
is registered as a practicing
professional engineer. Right, panel of
500 penalty units. I don't know if
there's a monetary value assigned to
penalty units. I don't know how much
that is. Now, it's an offense to hold
out to be registered or endorsed without
registration. A person who is not
registered as a practicing professional
engineer in a particular area of
engineering must not represent that the
person is able to provide professional
engineering services in that area of
engineering. So, you are not able to
say, "Hey, I can provide you
professional engineering services." And
some I I can kind of agree with that, I
guess, but we'll we'll get to that. A
person who is not an endorsed building
engineer must not represent that the
person is an endorsed building engineer
and therein you can see right there
where the catalyst for this bill has
come from. It's, you know, it's from the
building sector and hence the
electronics industry that I and we care
about being caught up in it. A person
who is not registered as a
non-practicing professional engineer
must not represent that the person is
registered as a non-practicing
professional engineer.
Huh? And here's the doozy. A person who
is not a registered professional
engineer must not use the title
professional
engineer.
Yeah, let that sink in. So, what they're
trying to do here is actually protect
the word professional engineer. Now,
they are not through this bill they are
not able to protect just the word
engineer, it's only professional
engineer. So, let's actually call up the
Macquarie Dictionary, shall we, which is
the standard dictionary the legal
dictionary here in Australia. What does
professional mean? Professional,
following an occupation as a means of
livelihood or for gain. A professional
actor. Relating or appropriate to a
profession. Making a business of
something not properly to be regarded as
a business. Undertaken or engaged in as
a means of livelihood for a gain.
Someone who makes a business of an
occupation. An expert in a game or
sport. So, it's not illegal in
Australia, even with the passing of this
bill, to call yourself an engineer. But,
when you add professional to the front
of it, even professional is implying
that's what you do for your vocation.
Hence, in my previous video talking
about how to become an engineer, if
you're doing engineering work and that's
your vocation and that's what your peers
recognize you as. That's what your
company has called you. If you even if
you have no qualifications at all, very
common in this country for you to be
given the title of engineer, senior
engineer, whatever it is, engineer in
the title, because you've been given
that
by your peers, by the company, by, you
know, everyone like you're recognized in
the industry as having the skills to
perform that job as your vocation. And
that's the word professional. That's
what it means. But
you're not allowed to now, in Victoria,
you're not allowed to put the word
professional in front of it.
Unbelievable. So, we're basically gotten
to the point where it's similar to the
Oregon engineer Matt
Jahlstrom
was fined 500 pounds. I've done a video
on this, haven't I? I think I have.
Anyway, he lives in Oregon, and he did
this great research about traffic lights
and everything, and he is actually a
qualified engineer in his native Sweden,
but he's not a certified practicing, you
know, registered engineer in the state
of Oregon. And he simply
sent something into council, some
research into council about traffic
lights, and they slapped him with this
fine. So, he took him to court, a
federal court, I think, or whatever, and
he won based on like freedom of speech,
and he's allowed to call himself an
engineer.
So, yeah.
Woo. So, you can see what, you know,
what's next? Simply calling yourself an
engineer that you do for your vocation.
I bet you that's next. It's coming. And
I know what you're saying, "Hey Dave,
what's the problem, right? If you're
qualified engineer, just
get it registered or whatever." Yeah,
well, that's forcing people to join an
organization they may not support. For
example,
the Institute of Engineers Australia. I
was actually a student member way, way
back, but I I just don't want to be part
of the Institute of Engineers. Just like
the vast majority of electronics design
engineers here in Australia, we are not
members of the Institute of Engineers
Australia. It's just not a thing here.
It's basically uh, for your mechanical
engineers, your civil engineers, or
those management engineers who like to
have all those little fancy letters
after their name. Vastly more engineers
here in Australia are electronics
engineers a member of the Institute of
Electronics uh, Engineers, the IEEE. I'm
a card carrying member of the IEEE, but
I'm not a member of the Institute of
Engineers, and I don't want to be.
But, if you're in Victoria, it looks
like I don't know how you become
registered. I guess it's either through
the Institute of Engineers or this mob
I've never heard of, the Association of
Professional Engineers Australia.
They've got a blog post on this uh,
bill. Let's have a look. Doctors,
lawyers, and tradies must register to
get a license to practice their
profession, but there is no such
requirement for engineers. There still
isn't. A registration scheme provides
the government public with a peace of
mind that only qualified engineers are
making engineering decisions. Like, how
far down the engineering tree do you go?
Do you take that to software engineers?
Like, do you take that to network
engineer like, how far down
the rabbit hole do you go here? And here
it is, like the Victorian government
will continue to invest heavily in
infrastructure. And this is where it all
comes from, it comes from the building
and civil engineering sectors, which I
support being certified and things like
that. But, the electronics
industry, for someone who's just laying
out a PCB or like, come on. Not only
will a scheme assist the government and
public in making informed decisions, but
registration will develop your
professional identity as an engineer,
highlighting your skills and expertise.
Woo! At present, anyone in Victoria can
call themselves an engineer. Our
registration scheme serves to protect
your professional identity.
Think of the engineers. They're doing it
for the engineers. Only qualified,
competent, knowledgeable engineers will
be registered, filtering out those who
lack the appropriate skills and
expertise. When you register, you will
be admitted by the state as a
professional engineer, opening the door
for more jobs. It's all about you. You
can get a better job that pays more. You
can earn up to $25,000
more than their unregister than your
uh rogue unregistered colleagues.
Beauty. As well as status, your
professional identity is formed by your
ongoing commitment to your area of
expertise. Should registration pass the
upper house, you'll be required to
commit to your ongoing development
through a minimum log of CPD, continuing
professional development hours.
It sounds like an extra requirement.
However, all you really need to do is
document any training or development you
have done to move up the ladder in your
workplace.
Is my nose brown enough? Does that
qualify? You may be surprised at how
many hours of ass-licking CPD you do
during one single year. You can build
your hours through on-the-job learning,
seminars, webinars, and online courses
you have completed. Watch the EE V-log
and you can put that on your competency
What do they call it? CPD, continuing
professional development hours. Just
watch the EE V-log. Oh, can you apply
for registration? Take the test. It is
Well, according to this website, it is
only
applicable to 4-year Bachelor of
Engineering degrees under So, it's a
Washington Accord one. And I've done
You'll have to watch my previous video
for the Washington Accord. Basically, a
4-year qualification. So, it looks like
it doesn't apply to 3-year or 2-year
qualifications.
Wow. So, yeah, you'll have to watch my
other video. I go into the Washington
Accord and all the all the different
accords, different levels for different
course. So, what does that do to the
engineering technician three-year
engineering technologists or the
two-year uh network engineers or or you
know, other sorts of software engineer
you know, three-year software degrees
and you know, other types of ones that
aren't covered under the Washington
Accord. What happens to those? Not
allowed to call themselves a
professional engineer even they're an
engineer by vocation. They can't even
register even if they want to. You know,
that's the real problem with these sorts
of bills. They They try to be
all-encompassing and somebody's going to
come a gutser somewhere, guaranteed. So,
yeah, anyway, naturally the uh Engineers
um Engineers Australia, they welcome
this compulsory registration of
engineers and yeah, compulsory. Thank
you very much. And they're urging the
other states and territories to follow
Victoria's lead. So,
coming to New South Wales soon.
And everyone in Australia won't be able
to call themselves a professional
engineer unless you got the four-year
degree uh under the Washington Accord
and you pay your dues to either I guess
either one of these mobs or some other
Maybe I should
Could be good money in this. Maybe maybe
should start my own engineering
institute.
Winner winner chicken dinner. Yep, and
here's their latest post today. They're
gloating. It's been passed. Yay! Where
do I start? Here's everything you need.
Yep, ATTN you need a four-year full-time
bachelor's degree or master's from an
accredited institution. All is not lost
if you don't have this as part-time
equivalent degree or a historical
equivalent qualification. So, to get
registered you would need 150 hours
professional development in last 3
years. You've got to prove. Just prove
that you watched X number of EE blog
videos or just say you did and Bob's
your uncle.
You're welcome. Work experience, you
need 5 years experience in the field.
So, it looks like graduates now and in
the first 5 years you cannot
According to this, and yet this mob at
least, you cannot call yourself a
professional engineer. At least they
won't certify you. Maybe you can go to
the Institute of Engineers and they'll
give you great maybe you can, you know,
get accreditation as a graduate or
something.
But it's all about you. The whole system
exists to ensure you have a senior
registered engineers to work with to
build the experience needed to be
registered yourself. But don't stress.
You can't call yourself an engineer if
you've had to hit the 5 years, you just
need more time to build up your
professional development hours. And all
you need is three other professional
referees. They that have worked with you
for the last 12 months that have to be
registered themselves. Otherwise, bugger
off.
And a commitment to the code of ethics
which talks about professional contact,
integrity, diligence, and decent
decency.
Rules me out.
Well, I searched for code of ethics on
their website and well,
coming to get sir, I found it after
searching on Google. Here it is. I love
this one. Provide engineering services
beneficial to the economy. So, well,
looks like Solar Roadways aren't going
to be able to hire any Victorian
engineers.
I do like the stuff about whistleblowing
though. That's neat. Not behave in a
manner that would damage the reputation
of themselves and others.
Hello, but that goes against the
whistleblowing stuff up here. They they
basically tell you blow the whistle, but
then then don't damage damage the
reputation of others.
Well done. Don't misuse company, public,
and private property.
Yes, Mom. No more teardowns.
So, anyway, oh, leave the link to this
down below. You can have a read for
yourself. I'm going to have to read the
whole thing, but it's going to be boring
as bat poo really. You search for
electronics, right?
Electronics.
I can spell. I'm an engineer.
Not anymore. El- el- electrical only
appears once. Like they don't even
really go into the definition of any of
that. If you have to ask, you're
covered. So if I'm sure if I went to
somebody and said, "A- Am I as an
electronics engineer covered in
Victoria, covered even though I'm not,
but if you are in Victoria, are you
covered by this bill?" I'm sure everyone
will say, "Oh, yeah. Yeah, you are." I
think it would require a court ruling to
rule otherwise. So
anyway, I I know this is like par for
the course in many countries. Leave it
in the comments down below if this is a
thing in your country and you can't even
I know many countries can't even call
yourself an engine- like the word
engineer without this, but it's still
not illegal in Australia even with this
to call yourself an engineer, but
professional engineer uh like I can
understand like chartered engineer for
example. The Institute of Engineers have
this chartered engineering level and you
have to go through a lot of rigmarole to
get yourself registered as a chartered
engineer. And sure if they want to
protect chartered engineer, I have no
problem with that. In fact, I fully
support it. That's fine and dandy. I'm
not going to go around calling myself a
chartered engineer, but simply a
professional engineer, the word
professional means that's what I do for
my profession, for my vocation to earn a
living and it's legal for companies to
hire anyone as an engineer even if
you're not registered or even if you're
not qualified and yet you can't call it
technically I do you can get fined for
calling yourself a professional
engineer.
Unbelievable. I
I
Like yeah, I said this bill is a good
thing for many industries, but it's
going to have unfortunately a side
impact on the electronics industry,
which I don't necessarily agree with.
But anyway, let us know what you think
in the comments down below and let us
know what's happening in your country.
Anyway,
catch you next time.